Few lessons ago we were talking about errors
and how to deal with them.
There are different kinds of errors, and I
want you to recall one particular kind.
Here is a little piece of that lesson:
The next kind of error is when you confuse
one thing for another.
Look at this code:
First, we create a constant.
Remember, it's like giving a name to something,
in this case — giving a name `length` to
a number 12.
Then, on the second line, we call a function
`length` and pass an argument — number 54.
But wait! `length` is not a function!
It's a number.
Numbers are not functions, not boxes that
do stuff.
And this is exactly how JavaScript will complain:
This is a **Type Error** — the type of the
thing you've used is wrong.
JavaScript interpreter wouldn't tell you what
the thing **is**, but it will tell you what
it **isn't**. `length` is not a function.
Type Error is like asking your cat to do the
laundry.
You probably wanted to ask your roommate.
In programming "type" is a classification
of information.
This is a general term, and different programming
languages deal with types in different ways.
As you know by now, JavaScript somehow can
see the difference between types.
Function is one type, Number is another type,
and you can't just use a number as a function.
`typeof` is a special operator that returns
a string indicating the type.
42 and 3.14 are obviously numbers, some combination
of letters in quotation marks is a string,
and true and false are boolean.
These are some of the types in JavaScript
— number, string, boolean.
NaN means "not a number", but the type of
NaN is "number".
Yeah, I know.
Another JavaScript weirdness.
Those are the rules of this language.
Types are helpful.
When we've tried running a number as if it
was a function, JavaScript started complaining
and we could see the problem and fix it.
If there wasn't any notion of types in JavaScript,
we would either see some bizarre unexpected
behavior or some mystic error.
Instead of clear "length is not a function"
we'd have something like "I'm sorry Dave,
I'm afraid I can't do that".
What if you create a variable, but don't give
it any value?
What type would that be?
It's not a number, not a string, not... anything.
Because there is no value, right?
JavaScript does something behind your back
in this case.
The variable without a value actually has
a special value — 'undefined'.
And the type of this variable is called 'undefined'.
So, for example, type `number` has lots of
potential values: 1, 2, -10, 69000, and other
numbers.
But type `undefined` has only one value — `undefined`.
There are two important things to understand
when it comes to types in programming: dynamics
vs static and weak vs strong.
In order to understand the difference between
dynamic and static typing, we first have to
look at how written programs become actual
running programs.
The code you write is usually converted into
some other form that a computer knows how
to run.
This process is called compilation, and the
period of time this happens is called "compile
time".
After compilation is over, the program is
launched, and the period it's running is called
"runtime".
Some languages check the types and look for
type errors during compile time.
Those have static typing.
Other languages check the types and look for
type errors during runtime.
Those have dynamic typing.
Another way to think about it: static typing
means checking the types before running the
program, dynamic typing means checking the
types while running the program.
C#, C++, Java, Go are statically typed languages.
If you create a number and try to treat it
as a function in one of those languages, you'll
get an error during compilation, and your
program will not even try to run — it won't
get to that point because a type error would've
been found before runtime, at compile time.
JavaScript, Ruby, PHP are dynamically typed
languages.
As you've seen before, if use the incorrect
type, your program does run, and the error
occurs only when that particular line of code
is executed.
So, the types are checked during runtime.
Actually, JavaScript *usually* doesn't have
any compilation at all, but that's a topic
for another lesson.
Dynamic typing is not worse or better than
static typing.
Both ways have advantages and disadvantages.
Dynamically typed languages are usually easier
to learn and to write programs in, but, as
you can imagine, it leads to more mistakes
and bugs.
Now let's talk about weak and strong typing.
Check out this JavaScript code:
Yeah...
This is...
Okay, what's going on?
Adding number 4 to a string '7' gives us a
string '47'.
JavaScript converted number 4 into a string
'4' and concatenated two strings — glued
them together.
JavaScript just took the liberty of assuming
this is what we wanted.
It's hard to blame it — what did we want?
Adding a number to a string — that doesn't
make sense.
Some other language, like Ruby or Python would've
just complained and not do anything.
Multiplying number 4 by a string '7' is, well,
28, according to JavaScript.
In this case, it converted string '7' into
number 7 and did the normal multiplication.
JavaScript does this a lot.
It knows about the types of different values
but when types don't match, it tries to assume
and convert from type to type without telling
you.
Sometimes it's useful, sometimes it's mindboggling.
This happens because JavaScript is a weakly
typed language.
It has the notion of types, but it's like,
"it's only a game, why you have to be mad?"
This has nothing to do with dynamic versus
static typing, which is about WHEN to check
for types.
Strong versus weak is about HOW SERIOUS DO
YOU GET while checking the types.
You can say that weak typing is relaxed typing,
and strong typing is strict typing.
Unlike dynamic vs static, the strength of
the typing system is a spectrum.
JavaScript has very weak typing.
PHP has somewhat stronger typing.
Python — even stronger.
And all three are dynamically typed languages.
So, JavaScript does a lot of implicit conversions,
but it also gives us tools to do explicit
conversion ourselves.
We can convert strings to numbers and numbers
to strings, boolean to string etc like this:
You can probably guess that implicit type
conversion is not the best idea ever.
Implicit means hidden, and hidden means it's
hard to understand and easy to make mistakes.
The behavior of the program becomes less obvious.
You write less code, yes, but the code is
more fragile and less understandable.