During the summer between case at cleveland and caltech at pasadena
暑假，在Cleveland的Case(凯斯理工学院)和Pasadena的Caltech(加州理工学院)之间
i had a summer job
我有了一个暑假工
writing compilers this algebraic
写一个编译器
this is the software that converts algebraic language into machine language
这是一个将代数语言转换为机器语言的软件
um i had a job writing compiler for Burroughs Corporation
我有了一个工作，为Burroughs Corporation写一个编译器
Burroughs was headquartered in Pasadena you know
Burroughs 总部在Pasadena
I mean the Burroughs division that was dealing with software was headquartered in pasadena
意思是Burroughs有划分，负责软件处理的总部设在Pasadena
And Case had recently installed a burroughs computer that i liked very much during my senior year
那时Case装了一台Burroughs计算机，我大四的时候非常喜欢它
some people from Thompson Rainbow Wooldridge approached me and said
一些来自Thompson Rainbow Wooldridge的人过来跟我说
Don, we understand that you can write compilers
Don，我们知道你可以写编译器
um we're going to put in a proposal to Burroughs to write a compiler for their machine
我们准备和Burrough商量，为他们的Burroughs 205机器写一个编译器
the Burroughs 205 for language called Algol which was just being invented at that time
给当时刚被发明出的Algol语言
the algorithmic language and international standard that was supposed to replace FORTRAN
这个代数语言和国际标准要替代当时最流行的FORTRAN语言
the most popular language at the time
and so Thompson Rainbow Woolders made a proposal to Burroughs for
因此Thompson Rainbow Wooldridge向Burroughs提出了协议
I believe it was seventy thousand dollars to create a Algol compiler for the Burroughs 205.
我认为是要7万美元来给Burroughs 205写一个Algol编译器。
the people who made this proposal really though were clueless about how to write compilers
虽然他们不知道如何编写编译器
so they hired me as a Case senior to do the job because they'd heard that i knew how to do it
所以他们雇用我这个Case的大四生做这项工作，因为他们听说我知道怎么做
and i had done this runsable and a couple of versions of other software at Case
并且我在Case已经做出过能跑的多个版本
spring of my senior year that they are showing me about this machine that bros had
大四的春天 ，他们让我看了这个机器
and i started playing around with the computer and i got interested  in
我开始使用这个电脑并且对这个项目很感兴趣
the project, but Burroughs turned them down they didn't give them the contract
但是Burroughs拒绝了他们的合同，没达成协议
so after Burroughs said they weren't going to do it with Thompson Rainbow Wooldridge i said
在Burroughs说他们不会和Thompson Rainbow Wooldridge合作
well wait a minute, maybe i'll write to Burroughs on my own and i sent him a letter and
我说也许我可以自己写一个给Burroughs，然后我写了一封信
said, you know for five thousand dollars i can write you another compiler
说我可以写一个编译器，要五千美元
five thousanddollars was a huge amount of money in 1959, in 1960
1960年，5k美元是一笔巨款
i mean a college professor was making eight thousand dollars a year or something like this.
当时一个大学教授每年能赚大概八千美元
i thought five thousand dollars was incredibly rich thing, you know to do. I said to Burroughs
五千美元的工作是一件报酬相当高的工作
i can do it in the summer except i won't have time to implement all of this Algol. I'll be able to
我给Burroughs说，我可以在夏天完成它，但我没时间给Algol实现所有的东西
do everything except procedures. i'll be able to which is actually the hardest thing to do in the  compiler
我可以做除了procedures的所有事情，我来写编译器实际中最难的subroutines， 来扩展语言的能力
which is the subroutines the ability to extend the language. Well, they wrote back saying
最难的subroutines， 来扩展语言的能力。然而他们回信说
we can't have Algol without procedures. You got to put procedures in too and so i thought about
我们不能没有procedures，你也得写它
it and figured out oh yeah okay i see how i can do it but you'll have to pay me fifty
思考后，我说我知道怎么做了，但是您得付我55K美元
five hundred dollars instead of five thousand, so they said okay, so i spent the summer of 1960
而不是50K，然后他们说Okay，
that's after graduating from Case. I spent the summer writing this compiler for Algol for the
1960年，我从Case毕业后，花了整个夏天为Burroughs 205和Alogol编写了编译器
Burroughs 205 and i wrote it but really i had it only in pencil and paper i
但实际上我只用铅笔写在了纸上还没能实际跑
didn't have it ready to go and i and then i would take it with me on as
i went out to Pasadena, and work on it there when i was at the burroughs plant in pasadena
我将带着它去Pasadena，并在那里工作
um so on my way out west, uh, i had a little volkswagen that might gotten from my parents and i
在我向西行驶的路上，我开着从我父母那里得到的一辆大众汽车
drove 100 miles a day and got a motel and sat down and wrote software. uh and took 30
我每天开车100英里，并在汽车旅馆坐下来写代码、写软件
days to drive from milwaukee to uh to Pasadena. every day writing a little bit of this software
从Milwaukee到Pasadena花了30 天，每天都写一点这个软件
then i got to Pasadena and had all my code had all my notes and started putting it onto
当我到了Pasadena，把所有的代码和笔记开始放到打孔卡上调试
punch cards and you know debugging it. And by christmas time i had their compiler for them and
打孔卡上调试。到圣诞节的时候，我有了给他们的编译器
and it was a machine that didn't sell very well so there weren't too many places in the
那种机器的销量不佳，所以世界上没有太多地方用
world. but i heard for the next 10 years that people in brazil were still using it a lot and so
但是我听说在接下来的十年里，巴西的人们仍在大量使用它
it was an interesting experience for me but the most important from my point of view was
它是对我来说是一次有趣的经历，但从我的角度来看，最重要的是
i had 5 500 dollars, which was enough to get married. so in the summer of 61 Jill and i got married
我有了5500，足够我结婚用了 ， 所以在61年的夏天，我结婚了
and it paid for our honeymoon trip in Europe which was our first time seeing the world
它支付了我们在欧洲的蜜月旅行，这是我们第一次见识这个世界